Hey everyone, it's Richard. You're
watching the plane bagel. It's been
about three years since chatbt first
launched. And since that time, we've
seen generative AI develop at a
remarkable pace. AI images and videos
have moved from horrific to nearperfect.
And large language models have gotten so
good that companies have started laying
off employees to replace certain
workflows with chat bots. But while it
certainly feels like we've entered this
golden age of artificial intelligence,
with some companies even teasing at the
prospect of artificial general
intelligence or AI with humanlike
cognitive abilities, there's been this
growing sense that maybe, just maybe,
we're actually in a bubble. One Bank of
America survey found that 54% of global
fund managers believed that we were in a
bubble. The International Monetary Fund
and Bank of England have warned about
the growing risk around soaring
valuations. Michael Bur, the investor
who famously shorted the housing market
before the 2008 financial crisis, just
this week announced a short position
against key AI companies. And even Sam
Alman, the CEO of Open AAI himself has
admitted that yeah, we're we're probably
in a [music] bubble. And many believe
that we're in for a repeat of the dotcom
crisis of 2000. given that we have
investors throwing money into a new
promising technological revolution
pushing valuations namely the cape ratio
to levels not seen since the docom
bubble despite the space not at the
moment anyway really making any money
openai who's behind chat PT and the
videogenerating Sora platform was
recently valued at $500 billion despite
seeing just over $10 billion in annual
revenue and losing even more than that
to its expenses and then there's this
monstrosity which you might have seen
circulated in videos like that from Hank
Green that demonstrates the incestuous
financial relationships we have in the
AI space with companies like Nvidia
effectively giving money to companies so
that they can buy their chips. Now,
that's a gross oversimplification, but
you get the point. The optics aren't
great. We're not really beating the
bubble allegations. So, what's going on?
Are we truly in for a do bubble 2.0?
Well, to find this answer,
we have to go to the source.
It's uh almost as inconclusive as me.
Joking aside, at the risk of throwing
yet another video into the sea of
content on the supposed AI bubble, I did
want to address the situation, explain
what's going on, why things appear to be
frothy, but also to highlight the key
differences between the current AI
situation and the dotcom bubble of 2000
without falling to the
sensationalization that often befalls
these type of topics. And to be clear,
this is not to discredit the bubble
claims or people like hankering or
highlighting real issues in the space.
is just to give more details and context
so we walk away with a better
understanding of what exactly is going
on. And to start off, it's probably
worth highlighting the key players in
the AI space. The first group are the AI
chip companies, the businesses who sell
the hardware needed to run these AI
models. This includes AMD and of course
Nvidia who's absolutely dominated and
been incredibly profitable with this AI
buildout which has helped skyrocket
their market capitalization to a record
$5 trillion making it the largest
publicly traded stock. Then there's the
infrastructure providers, the data
centers, cloud providers, whatever you
want to call them, uh the businesses who
buy or rent these chips, uh build data
centers to plug them into, supply
electricity, and then ultimately sell
the compute of these data centers to AI
companies themselves. These businesses
include the likes of Amazon, Microsoft,
Oracle, and a number of other companies
with uh at times mixed financials, but a
number of key players here do have very
strong balance sheets. Then there's the
AI companies themselves who buy the
compute from these data centers to
build, train, and ultimately run their
AI models. And here we have a whole mix
of companies from a financial
standpoint. On the one end of the
spectrum, you have firms like Meta, uh,
which is a massive company with very
good financials that's trying to build
its own AI models. There are then hordes
of AI startups with there being over
1,300 companies with valuations over
$100 million and nearly 500 AI unicorns
or companies with valuations of over $1
billion with notable examples including
Anthropic and Elon Musk's XAI. And then
of course we have the leader of the
space Open AI themselves. by far the
most successful company in artificial
intelligence and yet one of the biggest
money furnaces with a company targeting
revenues of 13 billion and losses of
$8.5 billion for 2025. And the company's
own estimates, according to one source,
see it burning through 115 billion
through 2029 with the company even
losing money on their highest $200 a
month subscription given that people are
using the service more than expected.
Now, because OpenAI is a private
company, meaning they aren't a publicly
traded stock, we have very limited
insight into their financial health, but
definitely a questionable business
model. Most users are melting Open AAI's
GPUs as free subscribers, after all.
Yet, this hasn't stopped the space from
building out aggressively. Open AAI
alone has made plans to build out up to
an additional 26 gawatt in data center
capacity and to date the company has
committed to around $1.5 trillion
in AI deals. This includes its
involvement in Project Stargate, a $500
billion initiative to build out data
centers in the US, a $300 billion deal
with Oracle to purchase compute power
over roughly 5 years, and deals to buy
chips from Nvidia and AMD, which the
Financial Times forecasts could cost 500
and $300 billion, respectively, with
these just being some of the many
arrangements Open AI has entered. Now,
numbers like these can easily lose their
meaning once they get high enough, but
it's important to put them into context
here. A gigawatt of power, for example,
roughly equates the output of a single
nuclear power plant and would provide
enough electricity to power just shy of
900,000 households, according to the
carbon collective. OpenAI is planning to
consume the power of 26 of these simply
to run its software. And that's just
Open AI's own investments. McKenzie
estimates that data centers themselves
and the infrastructure for these
companies will need to spend nearly $7
trillion in capital expenditures to meet
the demand for AI and traditional IT
applications. And while this is a global
figure over a 5-year period, to put it
into perspective, America's total
capital expenditures for 2024 was around
$ 8.3 trillion across all industries.
So, in effect, we're seeing the AI
industry spend a fifth of America's
total capital expenditures just in one
industry. Needless to say, it's a lot,
especially for companies that are losing
billions of dollars annually. And so,
because these companies are playing to
spend well beyond their current means,
they've naturally needed to call on
investors to help fill the gap. And so
far, they've risen to the challenge.
Venture capitalists have poured a record
of nearly $200 billion into AI startups
so far this year alone with over half of
total VC investments year to date going
into the space. But the cost of buildout
is only expected to increase. And that's
where this uh concerning kind of
circular chart comes into play. You see
the diagram lays out a number of key AI
financing deals and it demonstrates that
many are a bit circular in nature.
Nvidia, for example, has pledged to
invest $100 billion in OpenAI in return
for the company buying its own chips.
NVIDIA also invested in Core Weeave, an
AI data center that sells compute to
OpenAI, and agreed to backs stop the
company's services if it failed to find
customers. AMD supplied OpenAI with
warrants for it shares in return for
OpenAI buying its AMD chips with that
announcement alone sending AMD's stock
higher, which actually helps to pay
OpenAI for the whole arrangement. and
OpenAI announced a deal to pay $300
billion to Oracle for data center
capacity who naturally is going to turn
around and buy chips from Nvidia for
those data centers who is invested in
OpenAI. So you can see it kind of leads
to this
circle which uh has drawn some concerns.
[laughter] And even since this chart has
been published, we've seen even further
deals announced, including OpenAI's $250
billion deal with Microsoft's Azour,
with Microsoft being a major shareholder
in OpenAI and the company's $ 38 billion
deal with Amazon's AWS. And these are
just some examples. OpenAI isn't even
the only company involved in these sort
of circular deals. But at the center of
a lot of these deals has been Nvidia,
the one who so far has profited the most
from the AI gold rush. It seems like
they're investing that dragon's horde in
any AI company that pops its head up.
With there being recent announcements
around investments in Intel, Nscale,
Wave, and even Nokia, which I'm guessing
they're looking to make their chips
indestructible, which actually could be
a smart move, but it's led to concerns
that the so-called pick and shovel
seller is actually just paying gold
miners to buy its picks and shovels and
effectively propping up the space. Now,
to be clear, the arrows in this chart
aren't dollar for-dollar arrangements,
so the circle analogy isn't a perfect
one, but it could mean that Nvidia is
overstating its profits. After all, if
you're investing in your customers to
give them the cash they need to buy your
chips, then you're effectively selling
your products at a discount without
recognizing the hit to your profit
margin since investments aren't factored
into the margin calculation. And some
have pointed out that this type of
vendor financing became very popular
with companies like Nortell towards the
end of the dotcom bubble. Not to mention
that with us seeing AI companies
starting to borrow billions of dollars
to buy these chips and even putting
their current chips up for collateral
for some of these loans, it's led to
again this concern of this propping up
of demand beyond what's sustainable. And
amid this massive buildout and the deals
being made in the space, there's a
question about whether there will
actually be enough demand from end users
to justify all these investments. Bane &
Company, for example, estimates that AI
companies will need $2 trillion in
annual revenue by 2030 to be profitable,
which as noted by the Wall Street
Journal is more than the 2024 revenue of
Microsoft, Meta, Alphabet, Amazon,
Apple, and Nvidia combined and five
times more than the entire software as a
service market. And there just doesn't
seem to be a path towards that type of
profitability. Yes, 88% of companies are
using AI in their workflows to some
capacity and OpenAI itself has seen
remarkable user growth. You might
remember that Chat GBT broke records in
terms of being the fastest growing app
and the company now boasts 800 million
weekly active users. But only up to 6%
of these users are estimated to be
paying for this service. And the
majority of companies using AI, around
61% according to McKenzie, currently
don't see an enterprise impact on
earnings before interest in taxes. And
Croup earlier this year estimated that
AI revenue would only reach $43 billion
in 2025 and $780 billion by 2030, which
still represents pretty remarkable
growth at 80% a year, but less than half
of what Bane estimated would be needed
for the industry to break even. And
that's all assuming the AI companies are
able to deliver on what they're
promising. There's also the question of
the bottlenecks we're seeing form in the
space with the key one being
electricity. Building out grid
infrastructure takes years of planning
and development and that's assuming you
get through all the regulatory hurdles
of bringing online more fossil fuel or
even renewable plants which don't always
provide the consistent electricity
needed for data centers. And while
nuclear power plants have been a popular
choice for data center powering in the
US, the NRC application review process
can take 5 years alone to complete with
construction often taking another five
or more years according to the US EIA's
own website, which might be longer than
these companies are able to woo
investors. It's even led to some
companies like XAI skirting regulations
to set up on-site generators to try and
meet their electricity demand. Then
there's the consideration around the
lifetime of the data center hardware
itself. Over the last few years, large
tech firms have been expanding the
assumed lifetime of its servers,
spreading out their accounting costs
over a 4 to sixyear period. Whereas some
have argued that with Nvidia releasing
updated, faster chips every year, the
amount of time before these chips have
to be replaced is actually much shorter.
Which means that many of these companies
are going to run into higher replacement
costs than they're disclosing to
investors. And when you throw in the
sheer scale and concentration of the AI
industry with 35 to 36 companies
accounting for 99% of all AI token
spending, two companies buy nearly 40%
of Nvidia's chips and 10 companies, most
of which are involved with AI,
accounting for 40% of the S&P 500. The
failure of any one of these companies
could lead to fairly big shock waves,
not just in the space, but even the
markets as a whole. Not to mention the
real estate, utility companies, and
financing firms all involved in the
industry. And OpenAI alone has a lot of
the market's weight seemingly on its
shoulders at the moment. OpenAI's deal
announcements have added hundreds of
billions of dollars to the market value
of companies like Broadcom, Nvidia, and
AMD. If we see a pullback in that
company, it's going to hurt valuations
for many of these businesses, especially
when you consider how expensive many of
these companies have become with
investors pricing these stocks for
perfection, leaving very little room for
disappointing results. So yeah, it's
easy to see where the comparison with
the dotcom bubble comes from. In fact,
if you lump in software, computers, and
peripheral equipment, and other
information processing equipment, the
current private domestic investment in
IT as a percentage of GDP is back where
it was during the dotcom bubble. And
what's important is that you can still
see losses in the market, even if the
technology proves to be promising. The
internet did of course revolutionize our
lives, but also led to an 80% collapse
of the NASDAQ over two and a half years
as thousands of shaky.com startups
convinced investors that they were on
the frontier of a new highly profitable
business that ultimately would only
actually benefit a few players. So,
brings us back to the question, are we
truly in for a do 2.0? Well, while there
are of course parallels uh with, you
know, a new technology, investor
enthusiasm, and concerns that things are
overvalued, there are also a number of
key differences that make for a very
different setup here. For one, there's
valuations. Yes, the cape ratio, a
commonly cited measure of stock market
valuations, is fast approaching the
highs we saw during the dotcom bubble,
with a cycllically adjusted PE ratio
measuring the difference between a
stock's price and how much money the
company is actually earning. So how much
investors are willing to pay per dollar
of earnings per share effectively.
However, it's important to note that
with the cape ratio specifically, it
does include smoothing, meaning that the
earnings put less weight on any sort of
surge in profits we see. If you use a
more basic trailing PE ratio for the S&P
500, which only considers earnings over
the last 12 months, you can see that the
current ratio sits at roughly 30 times,
which yes, it's still high on a
historical basis, but it compares to the
dotcom bubble where we reached a high of
46 times. So, we aren't yet at the same
extended level of valuation, which
brings us to the second point, which is
that compared to the dot bubble, there's
actually strong financials and earnings
to back up many of these valuations.
Morgan Stanley, for example, has
highlighted that S&P 500 companies are
generating three times the cash flow as
a share of their valuations versus what
they were generating leading up to 2000.
And on a relative basis, there are
nearly half as many unprofitable
technology companies when compared to
2000 when 36% of tech companies were
losing money. Now, this doesn't account
for private companies like OpenAI or
Anthropic, which are highly
unprofitable. But these startups have
the backing of companies that are highly
profitable and are generally viewed as
financial strongholds. Many of these big
tech companies have very little debt and
hordes of cash on hand that they've
accumulated over the decade. So while
there is some evidence that leverage is
slowly creeping up in the space, which
could lead to some problems if that
continues. Currently, a lot of the
spending has been backed by cash on hand
or cash flows from these large
companies, which does limit the fallout
if we see one of these investments not
ultimately pan out. I also want to
highlight a few considerations when it
comes to the circular dealings in the AI
space. And this is not to really defend
these companies or argue that there's
not something, you know, kind of prop
upy going on here. Uh but when it comes
to Nvidia specifically, it kind of makes
sense that this is the approach they're
taking. Companies like Nvidia are making
so much money that it can be difficult
to find places to park that capital
without dragging down the company's
performance. So, it kind of makes sense
that Nvidia would invest in the
ecosystem that will ultimately benefit
its future demand. If the companies it
invests in are able to succeed with that
investment, then that means that they
are effectively incubating a future
customer. It's also not where most of
their cash flows are coming from. The
company over the last 12 months made $77
billion in operating cash flow and paid
out $24 billion in investing cash flow,
of which a fraction would be this sort
of vendor financing. And while there are
larger financing deals set up with
OpenAI for the future, for example, it's
important to note that many of these
arrangements are performance-based,
which makes sense given that there is
this perception that OpenAI may be
faking it till it makes it that it's
kind of talking out of its ass with with
these large deals that it's making,
given again just the scale of these
deals relative to its current revenues.
But the point is, Nvidia isn't just
writing blank checks with, according to
Bank of America, vendor financing only
representing a fraction of current AI
spending. It's also worth noting that
bubbles don't tend to just pop on their
own and part of the reason we saw the
dot bubble deflate was actually fairly
rampant fraud in the space. Many large
companies were discovered to have been
cooking their books to meet higher and
higher investor expectations. And while
yes, fraud is certainly possible today.
Uh but we have seen reporting standards
improve since the 2000.com bubble
because of these crises. We're also in a
very different economic environment for
better or for worse mind you with rising
interest rates often being cited as a
factor that killed the dotcom bubble
whereas currently we have the Federal
Reserve seemingly putting rates on a
downwards trajectory. And with all this,
it's important to acknowledge that we
could very well see Open AI's profits
scale from here. Again, as a private
company, we don't get much of an insight
into the firm's financials. But with the
company launching new services and many
businesses looking to lay off employees
to integrate more AI into their
workflows, there is a chance the company
is able to build its revenue. In fact,
just as I was finishing up this video,
it came out that Sam Alman expects the
company to reach $20 billion in run rate
revenue for 2025 and hundreds of
billions by 2030. Albeit, they're still
expected to be unprofitable in the near
term. Now, I don't know if that's how
things are going to play out, but
companies who invest in firms like
OpenAI do get more insight than we have
from the outside. And yes, companies
make bad investments sometimes. We
aren't today living in the metaverse
that Mark Zuckerberg desperately hoped
we would be. But assuming that all these
players are being perfectly irrational
is just as dangerous as assuming that
they're all being perfectly rational.
Now, with all that being said, I I do
think there's a bubble of some sort. To
be clear, this is not to downplay the
the very lofty valuations we have uh the
risk of a correction here. It's just to
try and distinguish between a crisis and
markets being disappointed with how
certain investments play out. It is true
that with high valuations, there's
little room for error and that leads to
lower expected returns for investors.
It's also true that the current
investment activity is just blatantly
unsustainable when you consider all the
AI activity going on. We're also seeing
many big tech companies lay off
employees, which some are pointing to as
evidence that capital spending and
slowing economic performance are
impacting operations, and we've seen
signs of strain on market liquidity,
which just means that investors might be
less willing to lend that money to these
AI startups in the future. It is also
likely that we'll see a consolidation of
the space, similar to what we saw with
the do- bubble. The truth is, we just
don't have enough demand for 500 AI
unicorns. And in fact, there's a lot of
good research that highlights that
technological revolutions have
historically been bad investments on
average, given that they tend to lead to
this boom and bust in market prices. And
the attrition experienced by all the
companies throwing their names in the
hat has a negative impact on market
returns. Even if the technology goes on
to be successfully adopted as companies
like Netscape perfectly highlighted
during the dotcom bubble, being the
market leader during the technologies
rollout doesn't guarantee that
leadership spot in the future. And if
you've never heard of Netscape before,
kind of perfectly illustrates the point.
But the point is, we just don't know
yet. AI is a new technology that could
prove very promising and could lead to a
lot of profits for these companies. Or
demand just might never meet the high
expectations that companies like Open AI
ultimately have. We could be in for a
metaverse 2.0. I would think this is
probably a little more promising than
that, but you get my point. Not to
mention that at any point we could have
a geopolitical event, a headline, a new
development that completely changes what
we were expecting to happen. And even if
we are ultimately in a bubble, timing
such a thing is near impossible. Alan
Greenspan, for example, the federal
chair at the time, called out the
irrational exuberance of companies back
in December of 1996, over 3 years before
the bubble would ultimately collapse.
And with companies like Meta viewing the
risk of underinvesting as higher than
the risk of overinvesting, these rallies
can ultimately last as long as investors
are willing to pile money into the
space. Yes, at some point these
companies will have to transition from
surviving on investor funds to uh
earning customer revenues to fund their
operations. But how long of a timeline
we face until that has to happen remains
to be seen. So hopefully you found this
video helpful. As always, it's important
to take a balanced view. There's just a
flurry of variables that make it
impossible to predict how things are
going to play out. So, while you
certainly don't want to get caught up in
the AI hype and, you know, throwing all
your money in Nvidia because you have
Chad GBT making Studio Gibbly versions
of yourself, it's worth hearing all the
arguments. Thanks for watching. If you
like this video, please do make sure to
like, subscribe, all that good stuff. It
does help the channel tremendously. Let
me know your thoughts on the AI bubble.
Uh, do you think things are overhyped at
this point or do you think concerns are
overblown? Any and all thoughts welcomed
in the comments down below. Uh, thanks
again for joining me and as always,
be safe out